Guide to the Browning-Monclair Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Browning-Monclar collection
1825-1965
1825-1850
GEN MSS 84
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
3.25
(5 boxes)
The collection contains correspondence, dossiers, printed works, and other papers documenting the friendship between Robert Browning and Ripert-Monclar and the life and business career of Ripert-Monclar. Also included are twentieth century materials concerning efforts to publish the Browning-Monclar correspondence.
Ripert-Monclar, A., comte de, 1807-1871
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Browning-Monclar Collection was donated to the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library by Richard L. Purdy in 1984.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
ANDRE-VICTOR-AMEDEE, MARQUIS DE RIPERT-MONCLAR (1807-1871)
André-Victor-Amédée, marquis de Ripert-Monclar, was born in Apt, in the Vaucluse, on December 25, 1807. He studied law in Paris, was called to the bar in 1824, and became an auditeur in the Chancellery two years later. In 1829, he was appointed deputy public prosecutor in Marseilles. As a Legitimist, he was dismissed from office during the July Revolution. Monclar supported the Vendéen insurrection in 1832, and was arrested as he attempted to raise the countryside for the Duchesse de Berry. He remained a Carlist, and his 1831 voyage to England was in the service of that cause. While in London, he met and became friends with Robert Browning. During the next few years Monclar traveled and continued his study of economics. He was one of the proposers of L'Omnium, a credit system which has been called the inspiration of the Crédit Mobilier. In 1838 he married Marie-Clémentine de Jernyngham, a niece of Lord Stafford, and succeeded to the marquisate the following year.
He returned to public life in 1840 with the publication of Des banques en France, and became sous-chef of the statistical bureau of the Ministry of Finance by 1847. In 1848 he published his best known work, the Catéchisme financier. Monclar was an unsuccessful candidate for the National Assembly in 1848 and 1849. He pursued his economic and statistical studies; the Statistique du Piémont appeared in 1851, and Finances d'Espagne in 1859. He also planned and drafted a comprehensive history of credit, but did not live to complete it. Throughout his career, Monclar was an active member of several learned societies, including the Institut historique and the Société française de statistique universelle.
The Marquise de Ripert-Monclar died in 1864. The couple had two children, Joseph-Anne-Amédée-François, a member of the Foreign Service, and Marie-Thérèse-Gabrielle-Victoire. Amédée de Ripert-Monclar died in Paris on February 3, 1871.
Scope and Contents
The Browning-Monclar Collection contains correspondence and other papers of Robert Browning and Amédée de Ripert-Monclar, as well as related material. The papers span the dates 1825-1865, but the bulk of the material dates from between 1825 and 1850.
The collection is divided into two series. Series I, Browning-Monclar Papers, is housed in three boxes. It consists of letters and memorabilia of Robert Browning and correspondence, writings, and personal papers of Ripert-Monclar. Series II, Related Papers, housed in one box, contains correspondence, notes, and writings about the Browning-Monclar letters. There are two boxes of Oversize material.
Series I documents the life of Amédée de Ripert-Monclar, including his friendship with Robert Browning, which began during Monclar's 1834 trip to England. Material related to Browning has been placed at the beginning of Series I. The collection contains nine letters from Browning to Monclar, three of them in French, and one draft of a letter by Monclar to Browning. Topics include current French and English literature, English politics, Bentham's economic theories, Monclar's reviews and articles, and family news. Several of the letters provide detailed commentary on Browning's poetry. In a letter of August 9, 1837, Browning describes "the circumstances under which my poems were produced." Part of this account is very similar to his later explanation of the origins of Pauline. Three letters contain discussion of Paracelsus, which Browning published in 1836 and dedicated to Monclar. The letter of March 2, 1835 contains an account of the poet's theories which closely resembles the published Preface to Paracelsus. Also present is an album given by Monclar to Browning. While some of the album's contents date from after Browning's death, it also contains a portrait of Monclar and other memorabilia.
Monclar's analysis of the poem, the "Paracelse: Pensée," is located in Box 1, folder 21. The manuscript is interleaved with Browning's own corrections and amplifications of Monclar's comments, including a lengthy passage in which Browning explains the major themes of the poem. The collection also contains letters from Browning to W. J. Fox and H. F. Chorley concerning the publication of Paracelsus and letters of introduction by William and Reuben Browning. Further mentions of Browning can be found in Monclar's two English travel journals (Box 1, folders 27-28).
Nearly all of Monclar's personal papers were contained in numbered and/or labeled dossiers. These were organized by M. Barruol, who purchased the Monclar papers in 1937. As this order may reflect Monclar's original organization, it has been retained.
There are eighteen numbered dossiers and two supplements. Dossiers 1, 2 and 4 contain autobiographical notes by Monclar, including lists of important dates and events. Dossier 3 holds notes, drafts of notes, and essays, mostly dating from Monclar's student years. Dossier 5 consists of journals kept by Monclar in 1830 and 1831, while he was living in Avignon. Subjects include the July Revolution and its effects on Monclar, economics, Monclar's visits to the salon of Madame Recamier, and his impressions of a performance by Paganini.
Monclar's journeys to England are documented in Dossiers 6-9. Dossier 6 is titled "Voyage à Londres en 1834" and consists of a "Plan for Visiting London in Eight Days," a daily expense record, and a daily journal with brief entries. Several comments refer to visits with Robert Browning and the Browning family. Also mentioned are Monclar's calls on the Duke of Wellington. "Voyage à Londres en 1837," Dossier 7, holds similar records. Dossier 8, "Angleterre-Observations, anecdotes," contains drafts of essays on various English subjects, including one which opens "Le peuple anglais est le plus matérialiste de ceux qui habitent l'Europe." Dossier 9 contains the calling cards collected by Monclar while in England.
The next four dossiers are concerned with Monclar's writings, both published and unpublished. Dossier 10 consists of drafts, notes, and clippings about Machiavelli, perhaps for a projected article. Manuscript chapters of Monclar's unfinished "Histoire des institutions de crédit" are located in Dossier 11. Dossier 12 contains the drafts and corrected proofs of the Catéchisme financier. Finally, printed copies of three of Monclar's works can be found in Dossier 13. (For copies of other works by Monclar, see Box 3, folders 63-66).
The remaining dossiers are miscellaneous in nature. Numbers 16 and 18 hold letters addressed to Monclar. Dossier 16 is composed of brief business letters from various persons, among them Chateaubriand and Guizot. Ten short business letters by the Marquis de Fortia and ten by the Baron de Vitrolles are located in Dossier 18. A variety of personal papers is found in Dossier 17. These include two public appeals to the Duchess de Berry; an obituary notice for the Comtesse de Ripert-Monclar; notes kept by Monclar during his 1848 campaign for an Assembly seat; and a few letters. The dossiers labelled "Supplément" and "Feuilles diverses" are equally heterogeneous, containing such items as drafts of business letters, an essay on the Salon of 1834, and an incomplete essay on the idea of Genius.
Printed works can be found in Box 3, folders 63-67. These include copies of the Catéchisme financier and the Essai sur...le marquis de Fortia d'Urban, as well as Fortia d'Urban's Essai sur l'immortalité de l'âme.
Series II, Related Papers, is located in Box 5. It is divided into two sections. The first concerns Fernand Henry, who studied the Browning-Monclar papers and attempted to have Browning's letters to Monclar published. This section contains his correspondence with Monclar's son. Topics include biographical information and copyright negotiations. Also located in this section are Henry's correspondence with potential publishers, his transcripts of the Browning material now in Series I, notes, and a draft of his unpublished article, "Un chapitre d'histoire littéraire." The second section of Series II contains correspondence, notes, and a typescript of an article by Richard L. Purdy.
Banks and banking -- France; Poets, English -- 19th century; France -- Economic conditions; France -- History -- Louis Philippe, 1830-1848; London (England) -- Description and travel; Economists; Browning, Robert, 1812-1889; Fortia d'Urban, Agricol Joseph François, marquis de, 1756-; Henry, Fernand; Jones, Henry Festing, 1851-1928; Purdy, Richard Little, 1904-1990; Vitrolles, Eugène François Auguste d'Arnaud, baron de, 1774-1854; Ripert-Monclar, A., comte de, 1807-1871
- Browning-Monclar Papers, Series I
  - BROWNING, WILLIAM
    - ALS to Reuben Browning, 1834 Jul 15 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - ALS to Ripert-Monclar, 1842 Mar 25 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - BROWNING, REUBEN
    - ALS to Ripert-Monclar, 1834 Jul 28 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - BROWNING, ROBERT
    - ALS to Ripert-Monclar, accompanied by note of Fortia d'Urban, 1834 Dec 5 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Related Archival Materials note
      See also: Box 4, folder 69
    - ALS to Ripert-Monclar, 1835 Mar 2 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Envelope addressed to Ripert-Monclar, 1835 Jun 22 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - ALS to Ripert-Monclar, 1835 Jul 30 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - ALS, in French, to Ripert-Monclar, 1835 Oct 15 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - ALS photostat, in French, to Ripert-Monclar, 1836 Jan 11 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - ALS to Ripert-Monclar, 1837 Aug 9 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - ALS, in French, to Ripert-Monclar, 1840 Mar 10 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - ALS, in French, to Ripert-Monclar, 1841 Apr 29 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - ALS to Ripert-Monclar, [1854 May] (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - ALS to Henry Fothergill Chorley, 1844 Jan 3 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - ALS to William Johnson Fox, 1835 Mar 27 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Papers and memorabilia: sketches and calling card, 1834, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Album
      See: Oversize, Box 4, folder 70
    - Ripert-Monclar, André-Victor-Amédeé, marquis de
      - AL draft to Robert Browning, [1835] (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - ALS to Mme. de Ripert-Monclar, 1840 Jul 20 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      - Brockden, William
        - 2 ALS to Ripert-Monclar, 1834, 1835 (Box 1, Folder 19)
        - ALS to Charles Ripert-Monclar, 1842 Feb 23 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      - Paracelse: Pensée. Interleaved with Browning's comments., [1835] (Box 1, Folder 21)
      - Dossiers
        - No. 1 - Autobiographical notes, 1855 (Box 1, Folder 22)
        - No. 2 - Autobiographical notes, [ca. 1850] (Box 1, Folder 23)
        - No. 3 - "Old papers" - notes, letterdrafts, essays, 1825-28, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 24)
        - No. 4 - "Mémoires de mon temps", [ca. 1832] (Box 1, Folder 25)
        - No. 5 - "Souvenirs 1830" and "Souvenirs-Avignon-1831", 1830-31 (Box 1, Folder 26)
        - No. 6 - "Voyage à Londres 1834", 1834 Jul-Sep (Box 1, Folder 27)
        - No. 7 - "Voyage à Londres 1837", 1837 Jun-Aug (Box 1, Folder 28)
        - No. 8 - "Angleterre-Observations, anecdotes", 1837 (Box 1, Folder 29)
        - No. 9 - Calling cards, 1834, 1837 (Box 1, Folder 30)
        - No. 10 - "Machiavel" - manuscript, notes, and printed (Box 1, Folder 31-33)
          See also: Oversize, Box 4, folder 71
        - No. 11 - "Histoire des institutions de crédit" - ms. chapters 1-3, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 34-35)
        - No. 11 - "Histoires des institutions de crédit" - ms. chapters 4-12 and notes (Box 2, Folder 36-42)
          See also: Oversize, Box 4, folders 72-73
        - No. 12 - "Catéchisme financier" - draft, notes, and corrected proofs, [1848] (Box 2, Folder 43-49)
        - No. 13 - Printed works by Ripert-Monclar, 1840-1859
          - Statistique du Piémont. Paris, 1851 (Box 2, Folder 50)
          - Finances de l'Espagne. Paris, 1859 (Box 2, Folder 50)
        - No. 14 - Proposals for an edition of the works of François de Ripert-Monclar, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 51)
        - No. 15 - "Peinture" - notes and drafts, 1827-31, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 52)
        - No. 16 - Letters to Ripert-Monclar, 1829-66, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 53-56)
        - No. 17 - Miscellaneous papers, 1832-64, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 57-59)
        - No. 18 - Letters to Ripert-Monclar: (Box 3, Folder 60)
          - 10 ALS of Baron de Vitrolles, 1836-39
          - 10 ALS of the Marquis de Fortia d'Urban, 1829-38
      - "Supplément - pièces diverses" - letters and ms. notes (Box 3, Folder 61)
      - "Feuilles diverses, à classer." - notes and drafts (Box 3, Folder 62)
  - PRINTED WORKS:
    - Des banques en France. Paris, 1840 (Box 3, Folder 63)
    - Catéchisme financier. Paris (Box 3, Folder 64)
      See also: Oversize, Box 4, folder 74
    - "Aux électeurs du départment des Basses-Alpes" in Le Socialiste des Basses-Alpes, 1848 Dec 31 (Box 3, Folder 65)
    - Essai sur...le marquis de Fortia d'Urban. Paris. (photocopy), 1840 (Box 3, Folder 66)
    - Fortia d'Urban, marquis de. Essai sur l'immortalité de l'âme et sur la résurrection. Paris., 1835 (Box 3, Folder 67)
    - Papers and memorabilia: calling cards, photographs (Box 3, Folder 68)
    - Portrait of Ripert-Monclar and Monclar family history:
      See: Oversize, Box 4, folder 75
- Related Papers, Series II
  - HENRY, FERNAND
    - Ripert-Monclar, Joseph, comte de. AL draft to Sotheby., [1913] (Box 5, Folder 76)
    - Correspondence with François de Ripert-Monclar, 1914 Jan-Jul (Box 5, Folder 77-78)
    - Correspondence with Henry Festing Jones and Reginald Smith, 1914 Jun-Jul (Box 5, Folder 79)
    - "Dossier": transcripts of Browning-Monclar letters and of Paracelse: Pensée, [1914?] (Box 5, Folder 80)
    - Notes on Robert Browning and Amédée de Ripert-Monclar, [1914?] (Box 5, Folder 81)
    - "Un chapitre d'histoire littéraire: Robert Browning et le comte A. de Ripert-Monclar," article draft, [1914] (Box 5, Folder 82)
  - PURDY, RICHARD L.
    - Correspondence, 1937-48, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 83-85)
    - Notes, clippings, and printed items, 1937-65, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 86)
    - "Robert Browning and Amédée de Ripert-Monclar: An Early Friendship", [1945] (Box 5, Folder 87)
- Oversize
  - BROWNING, ROBERT
    - ALS to Ripert-Monclar, 1834 Dec 5 (Box 4, Folder 69)
    - Album given to Browning by Ripert-Monclar, 1838-95, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 70)
  - RIPERT-MONCLAR, ANDRE VICTOR AMEDEE
    - Dossier 10: articles on Machiavelli in the Journal des Débats, 1844 Sep (Box 4, Folder 71)
    - Dossier 11: "Histoire des banques," in unidentified newspaper, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 72)
    - Dossier 11: "Vie de Guillaume III" in the Journal des Débats, 1839 Aug 11 (Box 4, Folder 73)
    - Catéchisme financier, in Journal des Basses-Alpes, 1849 Jan-Mar (Box 4, Folder 74)
    - Portrait of Ripert-Monclar and Monclar family history, 1830, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 75)